PETER HAUSLOHNER, Ph.D., MBA, MPH 711-1450 Pennyfarthing Drive Vancouver, BC V6J 4X8 CANADA

Telephone: +1 604 733 8165 (home); +1 778 320 0181 (mobile)

E-mail: phausloh@telus.net

Trained in public health, finance, and government, Peter has nearly 30 years of professional experience as project director, health programming and management consultant, housing developer, policy analyst, researcher, diplomat, author, and educator. He has expertise in health care financing, primary health care strengthening, pharmaceutical financing and management, and HIV/AIDS. His technical skills include work planning and budgeting, financial modeling, project design and evaluation, and health services research. He has a Ph.D. in political science, an MBA, and, most recently, an MPH from Johns Hopkins University (2009). Fluent in Russian, Peter is a US citizen currently residing in Canada.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2007-2009

Vancouver Coastal Health Authority Vancouver, BC, Canada

Management Consultant, Mental Health & Addictions Services, North Shore & Coastal Health Services Delivery Area. On part-time basis (two days/week), helped guide extensive internal "change processes" in response to comprehensive external review of Coastal Mental Health & Addictions Program; supported newly established public-private advisory committee and working groups, including facilitation of work planning; and conducted wide range of health services utilization studies, including emergency room attendance by mental health & addictions patients and prospective demand for geriatric psychiatry hospital care.

2005-2006

Abt Associates, Inc. Bethesda, MD, USA & Baku, Azerbaijan

Senior Associate/Chief of Party, Primary Health Care Strengthening Project in Azerbaijan. Directed (for 13 months) \$5.3 million project funded by USAID to promote health care reform in Azerbaijan, including the strengthening of primary care services and overall health system financing. Led team comprised of four organizations and project staff of 15-20. Personally assisted Azerbaijan Ministry of Health (MOH) to prepare, and to secure financing for, \$86.5 million, 6-year investment project in health reform, co-financed by World Bank; escorted Minister of Health and deputy Minister of Finance on 5-day "study tour" to Estonia. Contributed substantially to key project achievements: design and implementation of new surveillance system for avian influenza in 10 high-risk regions (in cooperation with MOH and WHO); development and presentation to Government of draft comprehensive health financing reform program (with MOH); design and implementation of baseline surveys of households and healthcare providers in 5 pilot and 2 control regions in preparation for World Bank health reform project (with MOH).

2001-2004

Montgomery Housing Partnership, Inc. Wheaton, MD, USA

Development Manager. Directed \$17.7 million rehabilitation of Pembridge Square Apartments, a 50-year-old, 17-building, 133-unit apartment complex in Wheaton, MD, in order to preserve affordable housing for low-income families and households. Organized acquisition of property, including short-term financing; selected & contracted architect, builder, and other development team members; led renovation design; secured construction/permanent financing (five different funding sources); and supervised construction. Project completed successfully and on budget in November 2004.

Peter Hauslohner July 2010

1994-1998

Abt Associates, Inc. Bethesda, MD, USA

Senior Associate/Consultant. Managed and/or assisted numerous projects involving health sector financing, privatization and reform in the newly independent states of the former Soviet Union, primarily for the World Bank and USAID. Selected assignments:

- Directed development of \$70 million project to reform rural primary health care services in three regions of Uzbekistan (for Uzbek Government and World Bank). Wrote proposal for \$525,000 design contract, awarded following international tender; opened Tashkent project office; recruited and managed international consultant team and local staff; led feasibility study for domestic vaccine production and assisted other technical work; mediated differences between Bank and Government over project objectives; wrote interim and final reports. Project approved by Government and completed successfully, with co-financing from first World Bank health sector loan to Uzbekistan (known as "Health One").
- Co-led design of pharmaceutical financing and distribution component of first World Bank health sector loan to Kyrgyz Republic (for World Bank). Participated in World Bank missions and project negotiations in Bishkek and Washington.
- Organized, designed, and led five-member consultant team in extensive, field-based study of financing and distribution of medicines in Kazakhstan (for USAID). Team's recommendations were later accepted by Government and USAID as basis for countrywide pharmacy privatization program subsequently implemented under USAID's ZdravReform project.
- Analyzed local pharmaceutical financing, manufacturing, distribution, and regulation during World Bank Project Identification mission to Uzbekistan (for World Bank).
- Developed and presented (in Russian) two-day seminar in Almaty on "third party" financing of medicines for pharmacists, drug wholesalers, and health regulatory officials from Kazakhstan, Kyrgyz Republic, and Uzbekistan (for USAID).
- Conceived, organized, and led five-day conference at Ministry of Health of Ukraine for health officials and local industry leaders on the structure and performance of the U.S. pharmaceutical industry (for USAID).
- Co-led field-based study of options for organization and delivery of health care services to expatriate and local oil- and gas-field workers on Russia's Sakhalin Island (for Exxon International).
- Managed preparation of Abt's proposal for a \$33 million USAID health care project in South Africa.

1991-1993

U.S. Embassy Moscow Moscow, Russian Federation

Special Assistant to U.S. Ambassador, Robert S. Strauss. Organized briefings, drafted official reporting cables, participated in Country Team meetings, met with visiting U.S. business leaders, assisted U.S. firms, and traveled widely throughout Russia on Ambassador's behalf.

1989-1991

U.S. Department of State Washington, DC, USA

Member, Policy Planning Staff, Office of U.S. Secretary of State, James A. Baker, III. Provided short- and long-term analyses of political, security, and economic issues in USSR; participated in high-level U.S.-Soviet bilateral meetings, as well as other bilateral and multilateral policy planning discussions; played active role in numerous intra-departmental and inter-agency ad hoc crisis and policy coordination groups.

1982-1989

Yale University New Haven, CT, USA

Assistant Professor of Political Science. Taught graduate and undergraduate courses on Soviet politics, comparative political economy, and international relations.

Peter Hauslohner July 2010

1977-1978

U.S. Information Agency Washington, DC, USA

<u>Associate Editor.</u> Commissioned and edited articles and book reviews for the social science journal, *Problems of Communism*.

SELECTED CONSULTANCIES

March 2010-present

Management Sciences for Health Arlington, VA, USA

Member of team fielded by Grant Management Solutions, a PEPFAR-financed project, to provide technical assistance to the Republic of Kazakhstan Country Coordinating Mechanism, with the aim of improving its governance structure, procedures, and operational capacity in accordance with the requirements of the Global Fund to Fight AIDS, Tuberculosis and Malaria. Team has so far completed two site visits in April & June 2010.

2004-2005

Center for Strategic & International Studies Washington, DC, USA

Unpaid expert on Russia for CSIS Taskforce on HIV/AIDS (chaired by J. Stephen Morrison). Collected and evaluated epidemiological and other data on HIV/AIDS in Russia; reviewed and assessed government policies; and accompanied one-week fact-finding visit to Moscow by head of CSIS Russian & Eurasia Program, including discussions with NGO consortium subsequently awarded Round 3 GFATM grant for HIV/AIDS and an assessment of Russia's nascent CCM.

January-February 2005

UNICEF

Moscow, Russian Federation

Edited English translation of *Children, Women and HIV-Infection in the Russian Federation* (Moscow: UNICEF, 2004), prepared by leading Russian experts and financed by UNICEF.

July-October 2004

Transatlantic Partners Against AIDS New York, NY, USA

Directed research and authored report on "HIV/AIDS and Social Orphans: Causes and Consequences of Child Abandonment and Recommendations for How to Alleviate It" for IREX and USAID.

EDUCATION

MPH Johns Hopkins University (2009)

Bloomberg School of Public Health

Baltimore, MD, USA

MBA The George Washington University (1998)

School of Business Washington, DC, USA

Ph.D. University of Michigan (1984)

Rackham School of Graduate Studies: political science

Ann Arbor, MI, USA

B.A. University of California at Berkeley (1973)

College of Letters and Sciences: Slavic languages & literature

Berkeley, CA, USA

Peter Hauslohner July 2010

GEOGRAPHIC EXPERIENCE

Peter has worked professionally in Azerbaijan, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyz Republic, Republic of South Africa, Russian Federation, Ukraine, and Uzbekistan; and he has travelled in more than two dozen other countries, including Egypt, Senegal, and Nigeria.

LANGUAGES

English: native Russian: fluent

French: intermediate (able to read professional material)

PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS

Member, Global Health Council, Washington, DC, USA

VOLUNTEER ACTIVITIES

- Played significant roles assisting multiple political campaigns for US House of Representatives (Connecticut's 3rd District, 1982; Maryland's 8th District, 2000 & 2002).
- Served three years on Montgomery County (Maryland) Western Area Recreation Advisory Committee (appointed by County Executive), the last two years as elected Chairperson (1999-2002).
- Still active in sports (downhill skiing, competitive men's soccer). Previously coached high school girls' recreational soccer team and served as United States Soccer Federation-licensed referee (1997-2001).

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS, PRESENTATIONS & UNPUBLISHED PAPERS

"Pay for Performance in British Primary Care: Lessons of the Quality and Outcomes Framework," unpublished MPH Capstone Project paper, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, December 2008, 36pp.

"Vertical Transmission of HIV Infection in Russia: Issues and Policy Dilemmas," presentation to Expert Working Group on the HIV/AIDS Epidemic in Russia, Center for Strategic and International Studies, Washington, DC, December 6, 2004

Deti, rozhdennyye VICH-infitsirovannymi zhenshchinami, i sotsial'noye sirotstvo: analiz situatsii v Rossii (Children Born to HIV-Infected Women and Child Abandonment: Analysis of the Situation in Russia), co-authored with T.I. Intigrinova (Moscow: Transatlantic Partners Against AIDS, 2004), 44pp. Available in English at http://www.gbcimpact.ru/files/upload/publications/857.pdf.

Strengthening Primary Health Care in the New Independent States: An Introduction to Five Case Studies, ZdravReform Program Technical Report 095, Abt Associates, Inc., Bethesda, MD, November 1997.

Privatizing the Pharmaceutical Sector in the Former Soviet Union: Results To Date and Lessons Learned, April 1995.

Additional publications and presentations available upon request.